Guide to the REPOhistory Archive MSS.113
Fales Library and Special Collections
REPOhistory Archive
1911-1999
1989-1999
Fales Library and Special Collections
REPOhistory (Organization)
MSS.113
18 Linear Feet (18 boxes)
The group, REPOhistory, was founded in New York City in 1989 and included multi-ethnic visual and performance artists, writers, filmmakers, and historians. Taking its name from the concept of "repossessing history," its purpose was to bring to light absent historical narratives involving, colonialism, race, gender, and class through public installations, performances, educational activities, printed matter and other visual media. The collection includes operation records, proofs of original artworks, promotional materials, source materials, and files of several founding members.
Provenance
The REPOhistory Archive was donated by REPOhistory in 2000. The initial organization of the collection was done by REPOhistory staff as they packed the materials for shipment. The collection was subsequently processed by members Alan Moore and Jim Costanzo. In 2012, Fales received metal sign mounts used to exhibit 5 signs from the Lower Manhattan Sign Project as part of an exhibition at 41 Cooper Gallery, Cooper Union.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Historical/Biographical Note:
REPOhistory was a multi-ethnic group of visual and performance artists, writers, filmmakers, and historians, founded in New York City in 1989. The group took its name from the concept of "repossessing history." Its purpose was to retrieve, relocate and document absent historical narratives at specific sites in New York City, through public installations, performances, educational activities, printed matter and other visual media. REPOhistory sought to question how history is constructed and insert the stories of peoples and events which have been omitted. Their work addressed historical issues of colonialism, race, gender, and class in a context relevant to current histories.
REPOhistory operated as an artist/scholar cooperative through 6 major public projects and many smaller events. Believing the arts essential to shaping a collective cultural identity and the relationship between art, culture and society to be confused, it instigated a questioning of the culture of the 1980s and the early 1990s.
Scope and Content Note
The REPOhistory Archive is comprised of the correspondence, meeting minutes, proofs of original artworks, promotional materials, source materials, and files of several founding members. Also included are complete sets of signs (artworks) used for 3 of 6 REPOHistory site specific installations, Queer Spaces, The Lower Manhattan Sign Project, and Buttermilk Bottom. The archive also includes various slides and photos that document specific projects and those members involved. The REPOhistory Archive is a part of the Downtown Collection at the Fales Library, New York University. The Fales Library is the primary special collections division of the NYU libraries, housing 200,000 volumes of English and American literature from 1700 to the present. Strengths of the collection include the development of the English and American novel, with an emphasis on the Gothic and the Victorian novel. The Downtown Collection, of which the REPOhistory Archive is a part, documents through personal and organizational papers, the artistic and literary Downtown New York scene from ca. 1975 to the present. SERIES DESCRIPTION Series 1: General Administration: contains four boxes of REPO general administrative files. The order of this series is maintained in the order it was originally kept. The series includes general correspondence, financial statements, fundraising materials, and meeting minutes arranged alphabetically. Series 2: Projects, Exhibitions, and Panels: divided into subseries according to specific projects conceived by REPO, the subseries are arranged chronologically.
Subseries: A The Lower Manhattan Sign Project, REPOHistory's inaugural project was inspired by the celebration surrounding the quincentennial of Columbus' "discovery" of the Americas. While the country planned to commemorate a carefully selected history of Columbus' legacy, REPOhistory created a project that presented alternative views of history.
Subseries B: Choice Histories: Framing Abortion, was a 1991 gallery installation investigating the history of women's global struggle for reproductive rights.
Subseries C: Queer Spaces, as part of REPOHistory's contribution to the Storefront for Art and Architecture's exhibition Queer Spaces, eight signs were placed at New York City sites where gays and lesbians gather for social and political purposes.
Subseries D: Entering Buttermilk Bottom, honors the passing of a community destroyed by Urban Renewal to make room for Modern Atlanta and the "New South." This site-specific public art installation consisted of signs, street markings, and a pavilion installation that illustrated the history of the community, as well as a reunion of former residents.
Subseries E: Voices of Renewal, following the 1995-96 project, Entering Buttermilk Bottom, this project represents the second phase of REPOhistory's public art/public history work in Atlanta's Old Fourth Ward. This Public Art Residency project was a collaboration by REPO artist Tom Klem and residents of the Fourth Ward's Glen Iris neighborhood. Working directly with those who lived these histories, six artist-created public history markers were created and installed permanently on the private property of those residents whose histories were unveiled and celebrated.
Subseries F: Out from Under the King George Hotel, for this project REPOHistory was invited to Houston, Texas, to create a public art project. They chose to document seven layers of history on the location of an abandoned hotel, the King George Hotel, which sat across the street from a homeless shelter and one block from the site of a new baseball stadium that was the cornerstone of the city's redevelopment plans for downtown Houston.
Subseries G: Civil Disturbances, was a public art project that presented two sets of 20 street signs created by teams of artists working in collaboration with legal scholars for more than a year and a half.
Subseries H: Circulation, an online project explores the city as body by examining the flow of blood through the city; blood as both a physical entity and as a metaphor for identity. The project can be viewed at
http://www.repohistory.org/circulation/index.php3
Subseries I: documentation of related projects.
Series 3: Publicity and Promotion: contains a box of materials that relates to publicity and the promotion of REPO and their respective projects. It includes press packets and literature as well as reviews and articles of their work. Series 4: Theoretical Material: contains a box of source materials used in researching specific projects. It includes articles and readings. Series 5: Members Files: contains files of core members such as Ed Eisenberg, Greg Sholette, Tom Klem, and Jim Costanzo. Fales has maintained the integrity of the order in which these members kept their files. Series 6: Slides and photos: contains slides and photos that document projects and events of REPOhistory. These photos are contained in box 14, and slides reside in three photo boxes numbered 15, 16, and 17. Series 7: Video, Audio, and Electronic: includes videorecordings, audiorecordings and magnetic [computer] disks. The videotapes and audiotapes include interviews and some source material used in researching projects. The magnetic disks belonged to members of REPO and include templates and files that relate to specific projects. Series 8: Artwork: includes complete sets of signs produced for site-specific art installations.
Arrangement
Folders are generally arranged chronologically within each subject/author heading.
The files are grouped into eight series.
Missing Title
Series I: General Administration
Series II: Projects
Series III: Publicity and Promotion
Series IV: Theoretical Material
Series V: Members Files
Series VI: Slides and Photos
Series VII: Video, Audio and Electronic
Series VIII: Artwork
Series IX: Ephemera
Accretion 2012 - Series VIII: Artwork
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Atlanta, (Ga.) |x Description and travel.; Atlanta (Ga.) |x History.; Houston (Tex.) |x History.; Correspondence.; Financial records; Art |x Finance.; Art |x Finance |z United States; Art and society.; Multiculturalism.; Multiculturalism |x Law and legislation.; Censorship.; Videotapes.; Racism.; Clippings (information artifacts); Art |x Experimental methods.; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century.; Theater and State.; New York (N.Y.) |x Intellectual life.; Culture conflict |z United States.; National Endowment for the Arts.; Social problems in art.; Politics in art.; New York (N.Y.) |x History.; Fliers (printed matter); Photographs.; Magnetic disks.; Artists and community -- United States; Audiotapes.; Political posters.; Printed ephemera.; Performing arts |x Finance.; Grant proposals.; Art -- Censorship -- United States.; REPOhistory (Organization); Sholette, Gregory; Wilson, Sherill D., 1953-; Lederman, Robert; Knauer, Lisa Maya, 1956-; Neville, Chris; Political Art Documentation/Distribution (Organization); Klem, Tom; Eisenberg, Ed (Edward), 1951-1997; Costanzo, Jim; Bogan, Neill
- Series I: General Administration
  - List of artists, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Artist resumes, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Art Matters book project, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Book distribution correspondence and documents, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1993 correspondence between MOMA and Repohistory (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General correspondence, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General correspondence, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General correspondence, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General correspondence (email format), 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fundraising - general proposals, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fundraising - general correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Fundraising - budgeting/planning, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Drafts for grant applications/fundraising letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fundraising information, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lannan Foundation visual arts grant, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Grant applications and correspondence - Art Matters, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Grant applications - Artist Space, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Grant from Cultural Council Foundations, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Grant application - Arts Forward Fund, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Grant application and correspondence - Manhattan Borough President, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Documents and correspondence - Materials for the Arts, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Grant application - Hudson River Middle School, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Grant application - Metropolitan Life Foundation, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Grant application - New York Council for the Humanities, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Grant application - NYC Dept. of Cultural Affairs, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Grant application - National Endowment for the Arts, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Grant application - New York State Council for the Arts, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Grant application - North Star, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Grant application - Public Art Fund, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Grant application - Puffin Foundation, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Grant application - Seattle Arts Commission, undated (Box 1, Folder 34A.)
  - Grant application - Andy Warhol Foundation, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - New York Foundation for the Arts - community assists, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Fundraising and financial reports, 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Fundraising and financial report, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Grant applications for REPO book - List and Kaplan Foundations, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Internal Revenue Service application for tax-exempt status, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Fundraising - NYFA Panel, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Fundraising - Lower Manhattan Sign Project, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Fundraising - LMSP grant guidelines, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fundraising - East Harlem, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Fundraising - Queer Spaces, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fundraising - Circulations, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fundraising - Entering Buttermilk Bottom, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Fundraising - Voices of Renewal, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fundraising - Foundation Contact Information, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Fundraising - research, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Fundraising - Neill Bogan folder, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Fundraising - other organizations' proposals, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Fundraising - individual foundations' literature and brochures, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Fundraising - individual foundations' literature and brochures, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Fundraising - individual foundations' literature and brochures, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Fundraising - individual foundations' literature and brochures, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Fundraising - loan agreements, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Fundraising - mailing lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Fundraising - letters of support, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Fundraising - letters of fiscal sponsorship, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Fundraising - pamphlets from libraries and museums, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Fundraising - private donors, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Letterhead, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Minutes from structural meetings, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Minutes of meetings of Repo Steering Committee, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Minutes of meetings of Repo Steering Committee (Neill Bogan), 1997 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Office leases and subleases, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Receipts for expenses, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Stationery designs, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Repohistory logo, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Expenses for Circulations, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Receipts for Urban Encounters, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Receipts and billings from Civil Disturbances, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General receipts, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Receipts for general operations and unidentified projects, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Misc. general administration correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Misc. general administration, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bank statements A, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bank statements B, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Bank statements C`, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Financial statements, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Corrections of mailing addresses, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - New York state tax exempt papers, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - New York state charities registration documents, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Treasurer's files - History Project, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Treasurer's files - Repohistory, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Treasurer's files - Repohistory, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Treasurer's files - Repohistory, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Treasurer's files - Repohistory, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Treasurer's files - Repohistory, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Treasurer's files - ledger and bank statements, 1990-1994 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Treasurer's files - financial records, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Treasurer's files - accounting report to fiscal sponsor, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Treasurer's files - reimbursed receipts, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Treasurer's files - federal tax returns and related documents, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Lisa Knauer's files, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Greg Sholette's files - minutes of meetings and narratives, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Greg Sholette's files - History Project proposals, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Greg Sholette's files - structure, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Greg Sholette's files - minutes of Circulation project meetings, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Greg Sholette's files - minutes of NY Lawyers in Public Interest meetings, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Greg Sholette's files - Lower Manhattan Project Sign Project texts, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Series II: Projects
  - Subseries A: Projects - Lower Manhattan Sign Project (LMSP)
    - Correspondence between Tom Klem and Jenny Dixon, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Lisa Knauer's papers and correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Lisa Knauer's administrative correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence - legal matters, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence - invitations, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence - general, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Original letters of support and city permissions, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Planning for the opening performance, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Edited texts for the signs and the map, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Sherill Wilson - advisor on signs, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Artist call for proposals, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Budgeting/planning, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Project outlines, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Project proposal drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Sketches and designs of drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Preliminary drafts for signs, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Jim Costanzo's notes and research materials, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Greg Sholette's notes and research materials, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Sign supplies, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Original proposal for signs, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Sign catalog copy, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - List of sites for signs, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - List of historical signs before LMSP, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Notebook/planner, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Proofs (master set), undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Proofs - sign art/texts, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Proofs - sign art/texts, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Flyer layout and proofs, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Research - historical society landmark, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Research - general, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Maps, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Snug harbor, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Educator towns - teacher handouts, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Contact information, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Umbrella organizations for larger public art project, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Sign project tea information notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Parade/performance of opening, undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Parade, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Parade - Neill Bogan file, undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Cloth to cover signs for day without art, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Announcements of related events, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Subseries B: Projects - Choice Histories
    - Proposals, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Artist space exhibition - correspondence and official documents, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - General information, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Articles and legal briefs, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Women's health information, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Gallery handouts and catalogue photocopy, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Race and class committee materials and readings, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Readings on abortion, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - 'Sexuality' receipts, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - 'Race/Class' receipts, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - 'Medicine' receipts, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - 'Law/Morality' receipts, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - 'Book/Chronology' receipts, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - General receipts and financial statements, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - General receipts and video receipts, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Subseries C: Projects - Queer Spaces
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence - legal matters, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Project outlines, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Research, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Contact information, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Meeting minutes, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Queers in Space, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Proofs, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Printer's proofs [OVERSIZE], undated (Box 76, Folder 3)
  - Subseries D: Projects - Entering Buttermilk Bottom
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence concerning specifications, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence between Tom Klem and James Malone, undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Project outlines, undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Budgeting/planning, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Meeting minutes, undated (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Contact information, undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Disk printouts of Donna Kessinger, undated (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Maps, undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Maps - Sanborn Mosaics, 1911 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Maps - Sanborn Mosaics - Civic Center east, 1911 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Maps - Sanborn Mosaic - Dickanny Alley, undated (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Maps - Sanborn Mosaics, 1932-1951 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Maps - Sanborn Mosaics - Civic Center east, undated (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Maps - 'Misc. other maps', undated (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Maps - unspecified, undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Research - official city documents, undated (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Research - white pages, undated (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Research - articles A, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Research - articles B, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Research - interviews, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Research - 'Neill Bogan', undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Research - 'U-Rescue articles', undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Research - binder, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Research - Atlanta Historical Society photo collection, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Research - bibliography, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Arts Festival of Atlanta -, 1995-1996 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Arts Festival of Atlanta - site works, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Original artwork, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Proofs for artwork, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Artwork [OVERSIZE], undated (Box 76, Folder 1)
    - Labels, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Misc., undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Subseries E: Voices of Renewal
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Project outlines, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Budgeting/planning, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Contact information, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Research, undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Resumes, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Proofs, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Maps, undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Arts Festival Atlanta, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Subseries F: Out From Under the King George Hotel